Guide to the National Education Association-Special Collections records, 1857-2015 NEA1007.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National Education Association Records-Special Collections
1857-2015
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National Education Association of the United States
NEA1007.RG
202.5 Linear Feet
Biographical/Historical note
The National Education Association (NEA) is the largest professional organization and largest labor union in the United States, representing public school teachers and other support personnel, faculty and staffers at colleges and universities, retired educators, and college students preparing to become teachers. In 2010, the NEA had 3.2 million members and is located in Washington, D.C. The group holds a congressional charter under Title 36 of the United States Code granted in 1906.
The NEA describes itself as a professional employee organization. The mission of the National Education Association is "to advocate for education professionals and to unite our members and the nation to fulfill the promise of public education to prepare every student to succeed in a diverse and interdependent world."
The NEA is a volunteer-based organization that relies upon its members to perform much of the Association's work. The members are supported by staff at the local, state, and national levels with the stated goal of "building great public schools for every student."
In 1857, Thomas W. Valentine, president of the New York State Teachers Association, issued a nation-wide invitation to teachers to unite in Philadelphia behind a common voice for America's growing public school system. After the meeting, the National Teachers Association (NTA) was formed with a membership of about 100. Minority educators were allowed to join at the start, but women were not allowed to join until 1866.
In 1870, the NTA merged with the American Normal School Association, the National Association of School Superintendents, and the Central College Association renaming itself the National Education Association. For the first 100 years of its existence, the NEA was controlled by administrators, and worked to further the interests of the "education profession" as a whole.
In the 1960's, after the first passage of a collective bargaining law for public employees, the NEA adopted union activities in addition to its operations as a professional association.
The NEA merged with the American Teachers Association (ATA), formerly the National Association of Teachers in Colored Schools (NATCS) in 1966.
In 1998, a proposed merger with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT) failed when it was rejected by NEA's Representative Assembly. Several NEA state affiliates have merged with their AFT counterparts, effectively forming a single association.
Over the years, the NEA has been a leader in national education reform and improvement movements. It has worked to improve the education provided to American school children through lobbying and campaigning on the local and national level as well as by promoting strong teacher education programs and continuous professional assessment and development.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records held by the NEA archives but not originating from any one office or department. The collection contains nine series reflecting organizational bodies and their records. The nine series are:
American Teachers Association; Arts and Exhibits; Awards; Birmingham Education Association; Joy Elmer Morgan Papers; Organizational History; Programs; Projects; State Affiliates.
Arrangement note
The collection is organized into roughly alphabetical series based upon the NEA's organization. Records have been allocated largely to their offices of origin and reflect the work done within the offices, departments, divisions and units. Due to the immense size of the collection and the constraints placed upon the finding aid by the archival management system utilized by George Washington University, the collection was further divided up into parts.
Organized into 9 series: American Teachers Association; Art and Exhibits; Awards; Birmingham Education Association; Joy Elmer Morgan Papers; Organizational History; Programs; Projects; State Affiliates.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research. Some files are restricted. Those files flagged as restricted are subject to review by Special Collections staff before being made available for research. As researchers request materials, a review of the documents will take place. Staff will remove any documents with social security numbers, employee numbers or other sensitive identifying information. Any document found including this information is closed for 90 years from date of creation, or until verifiable proof of a person's death is given. After these documents are removed the folder will be available for research. In some cases, items may be photocopied and redacted. The redacted copy will then be placed in the publicly available folder. All other materials in a folder will be freely available for immediate use and will be marked as having been reviewed by Special Collections staff. After folders have been reviewed using these procedures and the confidential materials have been removed, the restriction shall be lifted.
Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Teachers; Labor unions; Education -- United States -- History; Professional Employees; Professional Associations; Teachers' assistants; Maryland State Teachers' Association; Colorado Education Association; New Jersey Education Association; Idaho Education Association; Michigan Education Association; Ohio Education Association; Wyoming Education Association; Wisconsin Education Association Council
- American Teachers Association and ATA Affiliates, 1911-1986; Series 1; 3 Linear Feet
  Historical Note
  In 1903, a call was put out for a National Association of Colored Teachers by Professor J.R.E. Lee, who would go on to become the organization's first president. By 1907, the name was changed to the National Association of Teachers in Colored Schools (NATCS). Like the NEA, the NATCS advocated in issues beyond education, such as health and housing. In 1937, the organization changed it's name to the American Teachers Association (ATA). The name change came, in part, to encourage inclusion of educators in less segregated parts of the country.
  The Bulletin was first published in 1923. It was the official organ of the Association and continued to operate despite the fact that the editorial staff were not paid. This resulted in an irregular publishing schedule, but the journal operated almost continuously from 1923 until 1966.
  After years of working jointly with NEA on issues related to African-American education, the ATA merged with the NEA in 1966, with all state affiliates joining shortly after.
  Source: Perry, Thelma D. "History of the American Teachers Association" Washington, DC: NEA, 1975
  Arrangement note
  Series is arranged alphanumerically and then chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains material created by the ATA and material created in memory of the ATA or significant members of the ATA. The material includes photographs, articles, ATA and affiliate publications, event programs and memorials for significant figures, most prominently H. Councill Trenholm. A significant amount of the material was created after 1966 or is photocopied from an original.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  The American Teachers Association files are subject to review by Special Collections staff before being made available for research. As researchers request materials, a review of the documents will take place. Staff will remove any documents with social security numbers, employee numbers or other sensitive identifying information. Any document found including this information is closed for 90 years from date of creation, or until verifiable proof of a person's death is given. After these documents are removed the folder will be available for research. In some cases, items may be photocopied and redacted. The redacted copy will then be placed in the publicly available folder. All other materials in a folder will be freely available for immediate use and will be marked as having been reviewed by Special Collections staff. After folders have been reviewed using these procedures and the confidential materials have been removed, the restriction shall be lifted.
  Cataloged Black teacher association publications
  The NEA donated the contents of their library which included the publications from several Black teacher associations. These include the Mississippi educational journal, The bulletin of the Florida State Teachers Association, and The Herald from the Georgia Teachers and Education Association.
  These publications are all cataloged and available through the GW Libraries online catalog. These resources are available for use in the Special Collections reading room. Please ask staff for assistance.
  - 1. 1904 - 1908 John Robert Edward Lee (Ala.), 1944; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 1)
  - 2. 1909 - 1910 Richard Robert Wright, Sr. (Ga.), 1947-1974; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 2)
  - 3. 1911 - 1912 William Tayor Burwell Williams (Va.), Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 3)
  - 4. 1913 - 1914 Matthew Winfred Dogan (Texas), Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 4)
  - 5. 1915 Nathan Benjamin Young Sr. (Fla.), 1933, 1971; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 5)
  - 6. 1916 John Hope (Ca.), Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 6)
  - 7. 1916 William Henry Singleton (Tenn.), 1972; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 7)
  - 9. 1919 Simon Green Atkins (N.C.), 1919, 1970; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 8)
  - 10. 1920 John Manuel Gandy (Va.), 1920, 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 9)
  - 11. 1921 Levi John Rowan (Miss.), Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 10)
  - 12. 1922 Henry Lawrence McCrorey (N.C.), 1922-1970; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 11)
  - 13. 1923 John Andrew Gregg (Ohio), Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 12)
  - 14. 1924 May McLeod Bethune (Fla.), 1942-1982; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 13)
  - 15. 1925 William Walter Saungers (W. Va.), 1970-1972; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 14)
  - 16. 1926 Richard Sylvester Grossley (Del.), Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 15)
  - 17. 1927 William Albert Robinson (N.C.), 1927, 1970; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 16)
  - 18. 1928 William Jennings Hale (Tenn.), 1970; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 17)
  - 19. 1929 John Warren Davis (W. Va.), 1952-1980; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 18)
  - 20. 1930 Mordecai Wyatt Johnson, 1976; Series 1 (Box 3042, Folder 19)
  - 21. 1931 Frannie C. Williams (La.), 1977-1980; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 1)
  - 22. 1931 Harper Councill Trenholm (Ala.), 1970; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 2)
  - 23. 1933 Francis Marion Wood (Md.), 1944; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 3)
  - 24. 1934 John Willard Scott (Ohio), 1970; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 4)
  - 25. 1935 Garnet Crummel Wilkinson (D.C.), Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 5)
  - 26. 1936 Rufus Early Clement (Ga.), 1950-1970; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 6)
  - 27. 1937 Wills Carter Burch (D.C.), Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 7)
  - 28. 1938 Alphonse Heningburg (N.C.), 1971; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 8)
  - 29. 1939-1940 Corrington Lewis Davis (Md.), 1939-1040; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 9)
  - 30. 1941-1944 Mary Lee Williams (W. Va.), 1975-1977; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 10)
  - 31. 1945-1947 Walter Nathaniel Ridley (Va.), 1966; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 11)
  - 32. 1948-49 John Henry Brondhead (Penn.), Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 12)
  - 33. 1950-51 George William Gore, Jr. (Tenn.), 1950-1951; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 13)
  - 34. 1952-1953 Robert Clinton Match (Ala.), 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 14)
  - 35. 1954 Gerard Augustus Anderson (S.C.), 1971, 1976; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 15)
  - 36. 1955 Lillian Rogers Johnson (Miss.), 1969-1970; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 16)
  - 37. 1956 Elner Theodore Hawkins (Md.), 1973; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 17)
  - 38. 1957 Theodore Roosevelt Speigner (N.C.), 1970-1983; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 18)
  - 39. 1958 Charles Waber Orr (Ala.), 1958, 1983; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 19)
  - 40. 1959 Lucius Tarquintias Bacote (Ga.), 1970, 1976; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 20)
  - 41. 1960 George Washington Brooks (Tenn.), 1976; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 21)
  - 42. 1961 Lelia Anderson Bradby (S.C.), 1976, 1985; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 22)
  - 43. 1962 Lucius Holsey Pitts (Ga.), 1974-1977; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 23)
  - 44. 1963 Richard Vernon Moore (Fla.), 1963, 1970; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 24)
  - 45. 1964 John Rupert Picott (Va.), 1983; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 25)
  - 46. 1965 Cleveland Jerry Duckworth (Miss.), 1964-1972; Series 1 (Box 3043, Folder 26)
  - 48. 1966 President-Elect Hudson Lee Barksdale, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 3044, Folder 1)
  - The 1929 Summer Quarter: The President's Charge, Aug. 14, 1929; Series 1 (Box 3044, Folder 2)
  - 1932 Commencement Groups [Photograph], Series 1 (Box 3044, Folder 3)
  - Agreement - Howard University, 1986; Series 1 (Box 3044, Folder 4)
  - American Teachers Association History File, 1898-1965; Series 1 (Box 4655, Folder 1)
  - Journal - Alabama State Teachers Association [Photography], May 1961; Series 1 (Box 3044, Folder 5)
  - The Bulletin Vol. VI - Dr. George Washington Trenholm Biography, January 1926; Series 1 (Box 3044, Folder 6)
  - The Broadcast: Official Publication of the Tennessee Education Congress, 1956-1962; Series 1 (Box 3044, Folder 7)
  - The Broadcast: Official Publication of the Tennessee Education Congress, 1962-1964; Series 1 (Box 3044, Folder 8)
  - The Broadcast: Official Publication of the Tennessee Education Congress, 1965-1966; Series 1 (Box 3044, Folder 9)
  - The Bulletin, 1919-1930; Series 1 (Box 3044, Folder 10)
  - The Bulletin, 1930-1935; Series 1 (Box 3044, Folder 11)
  - The Bulletin, 1936-1952; Series 1 (Box 3045, Folder 1)
  - The Bulletin, 1954-1965; Series 1 (Box 3045, Folder 2)
  - The Bulletin Containing a Major Study of the NEA-ATA Joint Committee, May 1954; Series 1 (Box 3045, Folder 3)
  - Building Safe and Orderly Schools Tools & Skills To Make It Happen, Undated; Series 1 (Box 4930, Folder 11)
  - ATA Clippings and Miscellaneous Info, 1926-1965; Series 1 (Box 3045, Folder 4)
  - Constitutions and Bylaws of the National Association of Teachers in Colored Schools, 1917; Series 1 (Box 4655, Folder 2)
  - [ATA - Convention Reports], 1962-1965; Series 1 (Box 3045, Folder 5)
  - Dedication of the H. Councill Trenholm Room, May 3, 1986; Series 1 (Box 3045, Folder 6)
  - [Dr. H. Councill Trenholm - Tributes], 1963-1986; Series 1 (Box 3045, Folder 7)
  - H. Councill Trenholm Exhibit Papers, 1959-1960, 1986; Series 1 (Box 3045, Folder 8)
  - H. Councill Trenholm Memos, 1985; Series 1 (Box 3045, Folder 9)
  - The Legacy of Mary McLeod Bethune, 1974; Series 1 (Box 4008, Folder 20)
  - Letters Concerning NEA Presidents - Also List of Birthdays, 1972; Series 1 (Box 3045, Folder 10)
  - [ATA - Loose Items in Box], 1946-1962; Series 1 (Box 3045, Folder 11)
  - No Child Left Behind, Undated; Series (Box 4878, Folder 10)
  - Presidents - Addresses Throught the Years, 1942-1978; Series 1 (Box 3046, Folder 1)
  - Presidents - Listed by Native State Temporary Folder Project to be Delayed, 1971-1976; Series 1 (Box 3046, Folder 2)
  - Presidents - Listed by State of Residence At Time Elected, February 1972; Series 1 (Box 3046, Folder 3)
  - Presidents Pictures - Working Papers in Having These Pictures Made for the Archives, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 3046, Folder 4)
  - Profession Builder, January 2002; Series (Box 4879, Folder 1)
  - Project Management Seminar, Undated; Series (Box 4879, Folder 2)
  - Project H. Councill Trenholm: Correspondence/Memos, 1986; Series 1 (Box 3046, Folder 5)
  - "Some Background and Status of Higher Education for Negroes in Alabama" by H. Councill Trenholm, March 1949; Series 1 (Box 3046, Folder 6)
  - The Standard of Excellence in Teacher Preparation, Fall 2005; Series 1 (Box 4930, Folder 12)
  - Texas Standard; Official Publication of Teachers State Association of Texas, 1959-1963; Series 1 (Box 3046, Folder 7)
  - Texas Standard; Official Publication of Teachers State Association of Texas, 1963-1966; Series 1 (Box 3046, Folder 8)
  - Treholm Exhibit Materials, 1911-1931; Series 1 (Box 3046, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Teachers Association Bulletin (newsprint issues), 1964 February -1966 October/November; Series 1; These issues are newsprint and very fragile. Please handle with extreme care. (Box 3046, Folder 10)
    Issues cover the following years: 1964 February, 1964 April, 1964 May - June, 1964 September, 1964 November, 1965 February, 1965 April, 1966 April - May, 1966 October - November
  - Virginia Teachers Association Bulletin (magazine issues), 1961 October - 1966 February/March; Series 1 (Box 3046, Folder 11)
    issues include: 1961 October, 1961 December, 1962 January, 1962 February, 1962 March-April, May 1962, March 1964, October 1964, March 1965, 1965 May - June, 1965 October, 1966January, 1966 February - March
  - Virginia Education Bulletin, 1956 September/October - 1957 May/June; Series 1 (Box 3047, Folder 1)
- Art and Exhibits, 1959-1996; 1960-1987; Series 2; 2.5 Linear Feet
  Historical note
  Prior to 1990, the NEA passed a resolution that "every student, K-12, shall have fine arts instruction in school" A Fine Arts Committe was created to promote this.
  Series contains materials for art exhibits, including the material created by the Fine Arts Committee. This includes Committee minutes, advertisements for artists, commissions and contracts between artists and the NEA and annoucements, programs and prints for exhibits and promotional materials. There are some drawings and photographs included as part of a proposed sculpture to be built in front of NEA headquarters by Ken Valimaki. One box contains over-sized promotional posters from various sources.
  This series is open for research. Some files are restricted. Those files flagged as restricted are subject to review by Special Collections staff before being made available for research. As researchers request materials, a review of the documents will take place. Staff will remove any documents with social security numbers, employee numbers or other sensitive identifying information. Any document found including this information is closed for 90 years from date of creation, or until verifiable proof of a person's death is given. After these documents are removed the folder will be available for research. In some cases, items may be photocopied and redacted. The redacted copy will then be placed in the publicly available folder. All other materials in a folder will be freely available for immediate use and will be marked as having been reviewed by Special Collections staff. After folders have been reviewed using these procedures and the confidential materials have been removed, the restriction shall be lifted.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title, and chronologically within the same title.
  - 150th Anniversary Exhibit [Copies], 2007; Series 2 (Box 3318, Folder 5)
  - Art Exhibit 1987, Series 2 (Box 3048, Folder 1)
  - [Art Exhibit and Sale; Follow-up], 1987; Series 2 (Box 3048, Folder 2)
  - Art Invitations, 1987; Series 2 (Box 3048, Folder 3)
  - Art Jury Original Proposal Applications, 1985-1987; Series 2 (Box 3048, Folder 4)
  - Art Sale, 1987; Series 2 (Box 3048, Folder 5)
  - Art Sale Changes, 1987; Series 2 (Box 3048, Folder 6)
  - Art Search Proposal Acknowledgement Letters, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3048, Folder 7)
  - Art Search, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3048, Folder 8)
  - [Art Search], 1986; Series 2 (Box 3048, Folder 9)
  - Art Search, 1986; Series 5 (Box 3794, Folder 8)
  - Art Search, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3795, Folder 1)
  - [Art Search] 1st Page Proposal Sheets, 1986-1987; Series 2 (Box 3795, Folder 2)
  - [Art Search] Letters to Rejects, December 8, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3795, Folder 3)
  - [Art Search] Materials to be Returned, 1986-1987; Series 2 (Box 3795, Folder 4)
  - Art Search Proposals - Originals, 1986-1987; Series 2 (Box 3795, Folder 5)
  - Art Show, 1986-1987; Series 2 (Box 3049, Folder 1)
  - Art Show & Sale, 1987; Series 2 (Box 3794, Folder 7)
  - Artwork for Pioneer American Educators - Erle Prior, 1934-1953; Series 2 (Box 3792, Folder 1)
  - Bronze Coming to Fort Meyers, undated; Series 2 (Box 4039, Folder 1)
  - Capitol Building (color) - JD, March, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3292, Folder 3)
  - Catalog, 1987; Series 2 (Box 3049, Folder 2)
  - [Center for the Book in the Library of Congress], 1977-1981; Series 2 (Box 3303, Folder 4)
  - Committee for National Conference - Copy Negatives from Library of Congress Photos, March, 1996; Series 2 (Box 3292, Folder 2)
  - Commissioning A Piece of Art (A Chronology), 1985-1988; Series 2 (Box 3795, Folder 6)
  - The Education Department Building (JD), April, 1982; Series 2 (Box 3292, Folder 6)
  - Eurcelle Lewis, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3049, Folder 3)
  - Erle Prior - Original Artwork, 1946-1957; Series 2 (Box 3792, Folder 2)
  - [Exhibits by Year], 1959-1965; Series 2 (Box 3049, Folder 4)
  - [Exhibits by Year], 1966-1969; Series 2 (Box 3049, Folder 5)
  - [Exhibits by Year], 1970-1972; Series 2 (Box 3049, Folder 6)
  - February 24th Conference Call, February 24, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3049, Folder 7)
  - Fine Arts Commission [1/3], 1986-1991; Series 2 (Box 3795, Folder 8)
  - Fine Arts Commission [2/3], 1986-1988; Series 2 (Box 3795, Folder 9)
  - Fine Arts Commission [3/3], 1986; Series 2 (Box 3796, Folder 1)
  - Fine Arts Meeting, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3049, Folder 8)
  - Fine Arts Jury Committee - Appointments, 1985-1986; Series 2 (Box 3796, Folder 2)
  - Fine Arts Jury - Materials from Obermeyer, 1984-1985; Series 2 (Box 4039, Folder 2)
  - Fine Arts Jury Meeting, 1985 - 1991; series 2 (Box 4309, Folder 14)
  - Fine Arts Jury Meeting, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3796, Folder 3)
  - Fine Arts Jury Meeting, 1987, 1989; Series 2 (Box 3796, Folder 4)
  - Fine Arts Jury Meeting, January 17-18, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3049, Folder 9)
  - Fine Arts Jury Meeting, April 30 - May 31, 1987; Series 2 (Box 3049, Folder 11)
  - Fine Arts Jury Meeting, May 9-10, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3050, Folder 2)
  - Fine Arts Jury Meeting - Ken Valimaki, 1985-1987; Series 2 (Box 4039, Folder 3)
  - Fine Arts Jury Meeting - Minutes, February 5, 1987; Series 2 (Box 3049, Folder 10)
  - Fine Arts Jury Meeting - Minutes [1/2], 1988-1989; Series 2 (Box 3796, Folder 5)
  - [Fine Arts Jury Meeting] Minutes [2/2], 1988-1989; Series 2 (Box 3796, Folder 6)
  - [Fine Arts Jury Meeting - Minutes, Unapproved], April 30 - May 31, 1987; Series 2 (Box 3050, Folder 1)
  - Fine Arts Jury Meeting - Valinski Minutes and Notes, 1987; Series 2 (Box 3796, Folder 7)
  - [Fine Arts Jury Meeting] Working Folder, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3796, Folder 8)
  - Fine Arts Jury Minutes, November 6-9, 1986; Series 2 (Box 3050, Folder 3)
  - Fine Arts Jury Roster & Photos 1986-1987, ca. 1986-1987; Series 2 (Box 4123, Folder 13)
  - Fine Arts Poster, 1985-1987; Series 2 (Box 3797, Folder 1)
  - "Fly South" cutouts, undated; Series 2 (Box 4625, Folder 25)
  - "Fruit is Good for You.", Series 2 (Box 4599, Folder 1)
  - Future Stars, undated; Series 2 (Box 4039, Folder 4)
  - Future Stars Columbus, Ohio Newspapers, 1987-1988; Series 2 (Box 4047, Folder 6)
  - Future Stars Designs & Specs, undated; Series 2 (Box 4039, Folder 5)
  - Future Stars Photographs, undated; Series 2 (Box 4123, Folder 14)
  - Future Stars Slide, undated; Series 2 (Box 4039, Folder 6)
  - Future Stars Slides - 4, undated; Series 2 (Box 4039, Folder 7)
  - Future Stars Slides - 5, undated; Series 2 (Box 4039, Folder 8)
  - Future Stars Slideshow, undated; Series 2 (Box 4039, Folder 9)
  - Future Stars Slides - Oct. 22, Series 2 (Box 4039, Folder 10)